<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:base="https://sigmarootpi.com/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cogito, ergo sum</title>
    <link>https://sigmarootpi.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://sigmarootpi.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>An outdated habbit of spitting my thoughts.</description>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>Is Social Media a real enemy?</title>
      <link>https://sigmarootpi.com/posts/2025-07-17-social-media-nexus/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am currently reading &lt;strong&gt;Nexus&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Yuval Noah Harrari&lt;/em&gt; and just finished the first part--out of three--of the book. This part is about information networks and how, throughout human history, political ideologies such as totalitarianism, authoritarianism and democracy controls the flow of information. For example totalitarian government forces the information to flow through one channel, i.e government, resulting in the centralization of the information, thus of the power. No one can ask any questions or spread the information. Free media is not a thing in this situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flow of information in a democratic government is, in contrast, decentralized. Information can flow freely, and therefore, free media is very important. Press, a reliable source, can report and disseminate any news to the public, and people are free to criticize the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After experiencing the brutal past, we, the people, slowly moved from totalitarian/authoritarian governments toward democratic governments. However, in recent times, there has been a clear backward shift in many countries, including the US as well as EU countries. I won&#39;t go too much into details, but you can check out this book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, what amused me in this discussion is imagining the whole society as an information network and how social media such as Facebook (Meta now) can influence this network. The former is an interesting Physics problem, while the latter is a very hot topic nowadays. I will focus on the latter in this post because, due to my travels, I think I have an interesting perspective to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I grew up in a remote part of India, but due to research work, I needed to move around a lot. I spent my early twenties in different states of India: from  Mumbai to Punjab. For the past six years, I was living in Poland, and during this time, I got a chance to travel to other EU countries, meet people, and observe the influence of social networks in the EU as well as in my home, India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EU and India have very different societies. While EU countries are very open to change (it still takes a lot of work from people), India is very static due to its ancient past, making it resilient to any new change. However, please note that it&#39;s not very easy to compare any two societies due to their different social structures. There always exist some similarities as well. For instance capital cities of any country are often very open to new technology and fashion. So let&#39;s compare average &lt;em&gt;non-capital&lt;/em&gt; cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I partly agree with the current narrative that social media destroys society and manipulates people, I have also found that it resolves some problems. Of course, the nature of these problems is different in these societies. For instance, the problem of loneliness is minimal in Indian homes--especially in smaller cities--due to social interactions, but it helps to kill boredom, while in the EU, social networks are a good short-term cure of loneliness as well as boredom. My parents in India are not lonely, but whenever they are bored, it&#39;s easy for them to slip into the blackhole of reels. In the EU, people--including me and my friends--are more independent, which could lead to a lack of social interaction, resulting in isolation and loneliness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these subtle differences in social fabric, the implications of social media on both Indian as well as EU societies are similarly destructive. My reasoning here might have many gaps, so if you have any ideas, feel free to let me know. I would love to hear it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 05:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Rishabh Sharma</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://sigmarootpi.com/posts/2025-07-17-social-media-nexus/</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Social Media a real enemy?</title>
      <link>https://sigmarootpi.com/posts/2025-07-17-social-media-nexus/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am currently reading &lt;strong&gt;Nexus&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Yuval Noah Harrari&lt;/em&gt; and just finished the first part--out of three--of the book. This part is about information networks and how, throughout human history, political ideologies such as totalitarianism, authoritarianism and democracy controls the flow of information. For example totalitarian government forces the information to flow through one channel, i.e government, resulting in the centralization of the information, thus of the power. No one can ask any questions or spread the information. Free media is not a thing in this situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flow of information in a democratic government is, in contrast, decentralized. Information can flow freely, and therefore, free media is very important. Press, a reliable source, can report and disseminate any news to the public, and people are free to criticize the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After experiencing the brutal past, we, the people, slowly moved from totalitarian/authoritarian governments toward democratic governments. However, in recent times, there has been a clear backward shift in many countries, including the US as well as EU countries. I won&#39;t go too much into details, but you can check out this book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, what amused me in this discussion is imagining the whole society as an information network and how social media such as Facebook (Meta now) can influence this network. The former is an interesting Physics problem, while the latter is a very hot topic nowadays. I will focus on the latter in this post because, due to my travels, I think I have an interesting perspective to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I grew up in a remote part of India, but due to research work, I needed to move around a lot. I spent my early twenties in different states of India: from  Mumbai to Punjab. For the past six years, I was living in Poland, and during this time, I got a chance to travel to other EU countries, meet people, and observe the influence of social networks in the EU as well as in my home, India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EU and India have very different societies. While EU countries are very open to change (it still takes a lot of work from people), India is very static due to its ancient past, making it resilient to any new change. However, please note that it&#39;s not very easy to compare any two societies due to their different social structures. There always exist some similarities as well. For instance capital cities of any country are often very open to new technology and fashion. So let&#39;s compare average &lt;em&gt;non-capital&lt;/em&gt; cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I partly agree with the current narrative that social media destroys society and manipulates people, I have also found that it resolves some problems. Of course, the nature of these problems is different in these societies. For instance, the problem of loneliness is minimal in Indian homes--especially in smaller cities--due to social interactions, but it helps to kill boredom, while in the EU, social networks are a good short-term cure of loneliness as well as boredom. My parents in India are not lonely, but whenever they are bored, it&#39;s easy for them to slip into the blackhole of reels. In the EU, people--including me and my friends--are more independent, which could lead to a lack of social interaction, resulting in isolation and loneliness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these subtle differences in social fabric, the implications of social media on both Indian as well as EU societies are similarly destructive. My reasoning here might have many gaps, so if you have any ideas, feel free to let me know. I would love to hear it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 05:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Rishabh Sharma</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://sigmarootpi.com/posts/2025-07-17-social-media-nexus/</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jewish Cemetry</title>
      <link>https://sigmarootpi.com/snap/jewish-cemetry/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;blog-posts&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://sigmarootpi.com/assets/images/photo_posts/2025-07-07-IMG_2208.jpeg&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a hidden gem in a small town of Poland, Chęciny. I was here last week for a week-long summer school of Soft-matter physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was surprised to know that this cemetery dates back to 17th century. You can read about it &lt;a href=&quot;http://cmentarze-zydowskie.pl/checinyang.htm&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Someone told me that the language used on this gravestone is Yiddish. It might be wrong but using ChatGPT this is the translation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Here Lies Rabbi With all his deeds, the Righteous one who Passed away quickly. May his spirit come To repentance”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 05:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Rishabh Sharma</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://sigmarootpi.com/snap/jewish-cemetry/</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Siddhartha</title>
      <link>https://sigmarootpi.com/books/siddhartha/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;blog-posts-book&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://covers.openlibrary.org/b/id/6456720-L.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A delightful and quick read. Enjoying it so far.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2025 05:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Rishabh Sharma</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://sigmarootpi.com/books/siddhartha/</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Paris National Library</title>
      <link>https://sigmarootpi.com/snap/paris-national-library/</link>
      <description>&lt;div class=&quot;blog-posts&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://sigmarootpi.com/assets/images/photo_posts/2025-06-30-IMG_2119.jpeg&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like visiting libraries in different countries.  This one is special as it has a small forest in the middle. One can walk around this forest from inside the library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have heard from a Parisian friend that this small forest is also an ecological experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 05:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Rishabh Sharma</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://sigmarootpi.com/snap/paris-national-library/</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meeting Marcus Aurelius</title>
      <link>https://sigmarootpi.com/posts/2025-06-30-capital-museum-rome/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I was in Rome with my wife, and it turned out to be an exhausting trip, filled with mixed emotions. Like any touristy city, there were plenty of street sellers who were approaching people to sell souvenirs, food, and water bottles. It was irritating at times, but I kept reminding myself that I was walking through the city of Stoics--the same streets where &lt;strong&gt;Marcus Aurelius&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Seneca&lt;/strong&gt; once walked. So, I stayed calm and wandered the city as they might have done. We visited many places in &lt;em&gt;Rome&lt;/em&gt;, including the famous &lt;strong&gt;Colosseum&lt;/strong&gt;, its adjacent archaeological sites, “Roma Forum”, and several nearby museums. Honestly, each visit deserves its own post, but for now, I will limit myself to sharing my experience of visiting the Capitoline museums, aka “Musei Capitolini”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason for posting first about this particular museum is my fascination with Stoicism. I have mentioned it &lt;a href=&quot;https://sigmarootpi.com/posts/2025-06-23-wisdom-from-roman-empire&quot;&gt;earlier&lt;/a&gt; in my blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This museum is situated in the heart of Rome at the hilltop square (Piazza del Campidoglio). It contains many precious gems of the Roman Empire, such as the remains of ancient Roman temples, pottery, graffiti, and many historical statues such as the She-wolf, Socrates, and Marcus Aurelius. Entering this museum made me feel like I was entering in real Roman kingdom. Although there was a lot to see there, I focused only on looking for Stoics. This was partly because of a lack of historical knowledge and partly because of my tiredness as we were walking almost 15-20km every day. However, in the museum I found only one Stoic, Marcus Aurelius. It was still an amazing feeling to be there, to stand right next to his statue and feel its power. I haven&#39;t taken many photos from that museum, but wherever I saw Marcus, I asked my wife to take my photo with him. Every encounter with him was an emotional one, as if a student were meeting his Guru. However, the meeting was taking place around 2000 years later of the existence of the Guru.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Image Gallery --&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://sigmarootpi.com/assets/images/blog_posts/2025-06-30-IMG_1879.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;socrates&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://sigmarootpi.com/assets/images/blog_posts/2025-06-30-IMG_1846.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;marcus&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://sigmarootpi.com/assets/images/blog_posts/2025-06-30-IMG_1843.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;commodus&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also came across Commodus—-Marcus’s only son-—who was posing in a Hercules costume. What a pompous charlatan!!. I laughed and cursed him for his stupidity, which eventually led to his assassination. Seeing him also reminded me of his portrayal in the Gladiator movie—-I was watching it during this trip—-where he kills Marcus Aurelius. Although the movie is pure fiction, and historians believe that Marcus died of natural causes, reading about Stoics and Marcus’s only book, “Meditations” made me feel the plausibility of the hypothesis proposed in the movie. After all, Commodus was a fool and an immoral man, in stark contrast to his father, who was famous for his wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I am not here to challenge historians, and I might be an emotional fool. But seeing Commodus as a successor of Marcus did not feel right, especially considering that Marcus--and the four emperors before him--were not born kings but were selected and trained by reigning emperors. Ruminating on this, I finished my visit and went home.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 05:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Rishabh Sharma</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://sigmarootpi.com/posts/2025-06-30-capital-museum-rome/</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wisdom from Roman empire</title>
      <link>https://sigmarootpi.com/posts/2025-06-23-wisdom-from-roman-empire/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was reading &lt;em&gt;Letter of a stoic&lt;/em&gt; by Seneca and in the latest chapter I was surprised by advance nature of Seneca&#39;s thoughts--truly ahead of his time. He mentioned how people used to treat their slaves in his forefathers time--the master was regarded as a father figure and even was addressed as such--whereas in his time slaves were treated mostly with disgust and inhumanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although we abandoned slavery in most part of the world, violence toward the most vulnerable people still survived to this time. I have seen it in previous generation. To our shame, Seneca argued, almost 2000 years ago, that beating is for animals. So slaves (lets call them vulnerables) should be treated with respect and in friendly manner. This was remarkable to see, considering people still do violence, that these thoughts exists from so long time. Seneca was not aware of any known religion of modern times and yet he spoke similar human values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to share this because reading historical texts is always amusing to me, for the wisdom they contain, which many of us still lack. Whenever I read them,  I feel as though I am travelling back in time, having a conversation with an author, who lived several hundreds, if not thousands, years ago. Isn’t that fascinating!!.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 05:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Rishabh Sharma</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://sigmarootpi.com/posts/2025-06-23-wisdom-from-roman-empire/</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wisdom from Roman empire</title>
      <link>https://sigmarootpi.com/posts/2025-06-23-wisdom-from-roman-empire/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was reading &lt;em&gt;Letter of a stoic&lt;/em&gt; by Seneca and in the latest chapter I was surprised by advance nature of Seneca&#39;s thoughts--truly ahead of his time. He mentioned how people used to treat their slaves in his forefathers time--the master was regarded as a father figure and even was addressed as such--whereas in his time slaves were treated mostly with disgust and inhumanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although we abandoned slavery in most part of the world, violence toward the most vulnerable people still survived to this time. I have seen it in previous generation. To our shame, Seneca argued, almost 2000 years ago, that beating is for animals. So slaves (lets call them vulnerables) should be treated with respect and in friendly manner. This was remarkable to see, considering people still do violence, that these thoughts exists from so long time. Seneca was not aware of any known religion of modern times and yet he spoke similar human values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to share this because reading historical texts is always amusing to me, for the wisdom they contain, which many of us still lack. Whenever I read them,  I feel as though I am travelling back in time, having a conversation with an author, who lived several hundreds, if not thousands, years ago. Isn’t that fascinating!!.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 05:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Rishabh Sharma</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://sigmarootpi.com/posts/2025-06-23-wisdom-from-roman-empire/</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Snacky couple</title>
      <link>https://sigmarootpi.com/snap/snacky-couple/</link>
      <description>&lt;div class=&quot;blog-posts&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://sigmarootpi.com/assets/images/photo_posts/2025-06-19-IMG_1244.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are potato pancakes, famously known as &lt;em&gt;Aloo Tikki&lt;/em&gt; in northern India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But my wife made them cuter. ❤️&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 05:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Rishabh Sharma</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://sigmarootpi.com/snap/snacky-couple/</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Immigrant and Bureaucracy</title>
      <link>https://sigmarootpi.com/posts/2025-06-18-immigrant-and-bureaucracy/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last few days I am running around in my current city to get some official documents prepared and legitimised so that I can use them for job purposes in another EU country. Now in the beginning of my document-collecting-adventure I thought it should be a smooth process as EU is a union of countries so one document should be accepted in all EU countries. However, with time, I realized that that is not the case, especially if you are not from EU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, in Poland where I currenty lives, a no criminal record certificate (NCR) can be obtained by anyone who resides in Poland, and it is accepted in whole EU territory. The only condition is that the language of the document should be English or the language of the state in which it needs to be submitted. However the catch here is that the multi-language version is given to only Polish nationals, and not to non-Polish people. For non-Polish person it will only be in Polish. As a result its unacceptable in another EU state. To make it valid in EU first I need to validate it according to Hague convention (in simple terms apostile it) following which I need to translate it and then I need to validate the translation by doing a second apostile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its a tricky business and it needs to be done so there is no escape, and I am ok with it. You can argue about importance of bureaucracy and I get it. I respect the rules of my territory and usually try to adjust for small inconveniences. However what upsets me is the corruption this beaurocracy brings. Lets again take an example of NCR. Now to follow the procedure of dual apostile and translation, I need to go to Ministery of Foreign affairs (MFA) for which I need to book an appointment. But just to book a time-slot is not trivial. The daily released slots vanish so fast that in few moments whole day slots are gone. On the other hand, in market there are private companies who claim to already have these slots. I WONDER HOW!!!!. Now if someone want to take their service the amount of money these companies ask could be 4-5 times higher. This is outrageous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel the immigrants are the perfect target for these kind of scams because they will not speak against due to several reasons including language barrier and the fear of being detained. Also, native will never go there and deal with these issues. So no one gonna complain and politicians wont loose any vote. A perfect place for corruption to brood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, not to drag this post further, I only want things to be transparent and smoother, as well as pocket friendly. No matter how many documents they want, I am ready to provide but please save me from cheater and fraud companies. My time and money comes at the expense of public money, and I do not want to feel guilty about it. Neither I want to feel cheated in doing same formalities which native are doing so easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I wonder whether there is a way to resolve this problem or the need of beaurocracy is the only answer we have.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 05:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Rishabh Sharma</dc:creator>
      <guid>https://sigmarootpi.com/posts/2025-06-18-immigrant-and-bureaucracy/</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>